Rick Farouni | Curriculum Vitae

Massachusetts General Hospital/Harvard Medical School

✓ rfarouni@gmail.com • ♦ http://rfarouni.github.io/

I am a statistical modeler, data scientist, and applied deep learning researcher with expertise in generative and latent variable modeling. Currently, I am a post-doctoral research fellow in computational biology, working in the lab of Dr. Pinello at the Massachusetts General Hospital/Harvard Medical School. My research projects at the lab involve the application of Bayesian statistics, machine learning, and deep learning to epigenomics and CRISPR data. I received a PhD in Quantitative Psychology (statistics applied to modeling psychological and neuroimaging data), a masters degree in Mathematical Statistics, and a masters degree in Psychometrics from the Ohio State University.

Postdoctoral Research Fellow.

Experience

Massachusetts General Hospital/Harvard Medical School

Research Lab of Professor Luca Pinello, Molecular Pathology Unit

Massachusetts, USA 06/2017-Present

Projects - Haystack Pipeline: A Python bioinformatics pipeline for the identification of genomic regions

and their associated transcription factors. - Histone Code: Deep generative modeling of chromatin signal data across multiple cell types and histone marks with the goal of learning a latent representation of chromatin state

of epigenetic variability across different cell-types, cell-type specific cis-regulatory elements,

- dynamics (i.e. a continuous histone code). The modeling efforts involve applying a Variational Autoencoder (VAE) approach and its extensions (e.g. recurrent VAE) to sequential data. - Statistical Modeling of CRISPR Double Knockout Data: A hierarchical negative binomial Bayesian framework for modeling CRISPR-Cas9 Double-Knockout screen count data.
- Research Intern

Department of Biomedical Informatics Summer Internship Program

Research Lab of Professor Ewy Mathè, The Ohio State University **Projects**

05/2016-08/2016

Ohio, USA

- **ALTRE**: An R package and a Shiny app for the analysis of data generated from genome-wide chromatin accessibility assays such as ATAC-seq and DNase-seq with the goal of identifying

regulatory elements involved in the cancer epigenetic landscape. University Teaching Assistant..... The Ohio State University Ohio, USA

Models, and Data Analysis in Psychology.

Instructor of the Graduate Management Admission Test (GMAT)

2009-2012

2013-2017

Independent Tutor..... **Test Preparation Instructor** Moscow, Russia

Served as a Teaching Assistant for three courses: Repeated Measures Models, Covariance Structure

Teacher of English as a Foreign Language Teacher of General and Academic English

2001-2009

Moscow, Russia

Education

Graduate Teaching Associate (Statistics)

Ohio, USA

2015–2017

Academic Qualifications..... PhD in Quantitative Psychology

The Ohio State University Dissertation Topic: 'Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning

of Chromatin States'

The Ohio State University

Course Projects

Master of Science in Statistics

Ohio, USA

2012-2014

 Retinotopic Mapping of the Human Visual Cortex Using Independent Component Analysis (STAT 7560: Multivariate Statistics)

- (STAT 6750: Statistical Consulting) Master's Degree in Psychometrics The Ohio State University

- Modeling Categorical Perception of Speech Sounds using Beta Regression

- Bayesian Analysis of Noisy Images Using Markov Random Fields

(STAT 7730: Advanced Computational Statistics)

Thesis Project: 'Latent Variable Modeling of Categorical Item Responses in a Hierarchical Bayesian Framework'

Conference Presentations

Pennsylvania, USA

Ohio, USA

2012-2014

2011-2012

Seattle

2015

Joint Statistical Meetings Poster Presentation

Bachelor's Degree in Psychology

The Pennsylvania State University

assets/posters/jsm2015.pdf). Awards and Fellowships

Poster Title: Across-Subject Predictive Modeling of fMRI BOLD Responses to Faces using a sparse Bayesian Group Factor Analysis Model (available at https://rfarouni.github.io/

Graduate Student Conference Presentation Award The Ohio State University 2015 The Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences Summer Graduate Fellowship The Ohio State University 2015

the Voxels of fMRI BOLD Activity Patterns' The Social and Behavioral Sciences Summer Fellowship

The Ohio State University

University Fellowship

Journal Papers..

The Ohio State University **Publications and Software**

Project Proposal: 'Decoding the Pixels of the Face Image from

2015

2016

2014

2012

Preprint available at http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/10/14/080564.full. pdf+html (first co-author)

199067 (first co-author)

o Clement, K., Farouni, R., Bauer, D. E., and Pinello, L. (2018). Design and analysis of unique molecular identifiers for deep amplicon sequencing. (submitted, first co-author) Preprints.

Farouni, R. (2017). A Contemporary Overview of Probabilistic Latent Variable Models. arXiv

o Farouni, R. (2017). Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States. PhD Dissertation. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/

preprint. Preprint available at https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.08137

Dissertation and Thesis

!etd.send_file?accession=osu1492189894812539&disposition=inline

Software Development.....

GitHub Repo (private): https://github.com/pinellolab/histone_code_vae.

o Baskin, E., Farouni, R., and Mathè, E. (2016). ALTRE: workflow for defining ALTered Regulatory Elements using chromatin accessibility data. *Bioinformatics* doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw688.

o Pinello, L., Farouni, R., and Yuan, G-C. (2018). Haystack: systematic analysis of the variation of epigenetic states and cell-type specific regulatory elements. Bioinformatics https://doi. org/10.1093/bioinformatics/bty031. Preprint available at https://doi.org/10.1101/

o Farouni, R. (2014). Latent Variable Models of Categorical Responses in the Bayesian and Frequentist Frameworks. Masters Thesis. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink. edu/!etd.send_file?accession=osu1412374136&disposition=inline

o Histone Code VAE: Deep generative modeling of chromatin signal data across multiple cell types.

 Haystack: systematic analysis of the variation of epigenetic states and cell-type specific regulatory elements. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/pinellolab/haystack_bio.

Ad Hoc Reviewer

Ad Hoc Reviewer

Psychological Methods

- o ALTRE: A Workflow for Identifying ALTered Regulatory Elements using Chromatin Accessibility Data. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/Mathelab/ALTRE. Journal Review Service..... **Psychometrika**
- **Technical Skill Set**

- Scientific Programming Languages: Proficient in and comfortable transitioning between R,

- **Deep Learning Frameworks:** Experienced in using Tensorflow and Keras. - Probabilistic Programming Languages: Proficient in Stan, familiar with Edward.

Statistics and Machine Learning

- Neuroimaging data analysis: Nipype, PyMVPA, FreeSurfer, FSL. - Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) data analysis: R's Bioconductor core packages,

Bioinformatics and Neuroimaging Software

Bowtie2, MACS2, and bedtools. Cluster and High-Performance Computing - Good knowledge of running neuroimaging and bioinformatics analysis pipelines on super-

Python depending on computing goals. Familiar with Julia.

- computing clusters. Web and Software Development Tools
 - LATEX, Linux OS, Git, Docker, and Bash. Basic knowledge in website development tools such as HTML, CSS, and Jekyll.

Personal Details

- Country of Current Residence: USA
- Country of Previous Residence: Russia (12 years) o Interests and Hobbies: Theoretical Linguistics, Evolutionary Biology, Experimental Music Languages Spoken: English, Arabic, Russian, Spanish (intermediate), French (elementary)